A Guide to the Leftwich-Shepherd-Bowles Family Papers, 1854-1920
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Leftwich-Shepherd-Bowles Family Papers, 1854-1920
Library of Virginia
27988
.3 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Walter E. Styles of Chester, Virginia, 3 May 1973.
Biographical Information
Reverend James C. Leftwich (1799-1852) and Anne Bilbro Leftwich (1812-1864) of Bedford County, Virginia, had six children, including Frances Jane Leftwich (1833-1906), John William Leftwich (1835-1868), and Sarah (Sallie) North Leftwich. Frances Jane Leftwich married John Newton Shepherd (1834-1866) of Fluvanna County, Virginia, 12 February 1857, and they had four children. She was principal of the Edgewood Female Institute in Fluvanna County from 1866 to 1871. She later moved to Austin, Texas, where she taught and served as principal of the Austin Female Institute. John William Leftwich attended the University of Virginia and Bellevue Hospital in New York, New York. He served as a physician in the Confederate army during the Civil War. Leftwich practiced medicine afterwards in Pittsylvania County, Virginia, and also farmed. He married Martha Elizabeth Jones (1842-1908) 16 May 1860, and they had three children. Sarah (Sallie) North Leftwich attended Valley Union Seminiary and Hollins College. She married Thomas J. Shepherd (1832-1874) of Fluvanna County 17 April 1861, and they had four children, including Thomas Joseph Shepherd (b. 1868). Clyde Dennis Shepherd (1896-1965) was the son of Sallie N. Shepherd's son James Leftwich Shepherd (b. 1861) and his wife Susie Rives Jackson Shepherd (b. 1875). Francis Norman Bowles (b. 1901) was the son of Sallie N. Shepherd's daughter Fannie Newton Shepherd (b. 1866) and her husband Charles Knight Bowles (b. 1861).
Scope and Content
Papers, 1854-1920, of the Leftwich-Shepherd-Bowles family of Bedford, Fluvanna and Pittsylvania Counties, Virginia, consisting of correspondence, exercise books, notebooks, and photographs. Correspondence, 1860-1867, consists of letters to and from Sarah (Sallie) North Leftwich (Shepherd) (1839-1911), John William Leftwich (1835-1868), and Frances Jane Leftwich Shepherd (1833-1906) containing family and personal news discussing Sallie Leftwich's marriage to Thomas J. Shepherd, John William Leftwich's details of his Civil War service and life in Reconstruction Pittsylvania County, and Sallie Leftwich's concern over Thomas J. Shepherd's (her future husband) illness. Also contains a letter, ca. 1861-1864, from Ann Bilbro Leftwich (1812-1864) to Sallie N. Leftwich Shepherd containing personal news and a letter, 3 June 1882, from Thomas J. Shepherd (b. 1868) (her son) asking if he may come home. Collection also includes Sallie N. Leftwich's French exercise book, 1854, which includes transcripts of letters, 1857-1860, to family and friends, as well as Sallie Leftwich's accounts for cloth and other items; John William Leftwich's treatise, ca. 1865-1868, on growing tobacco in Pittsylvania County and F. N. Bowles' (b. 1901) chemistry notebook, ca. 1920, while a student at Richmond College. Collection also contains twelve photographs, including portraits of Clyde Dennis Shepherd (1896-1965), M. M. Sneed, [Gen. Ray?] Wood, and Bertha Caldwell; a book on sights from around the world, and a french language story book.
Contents List
- French exercise book, 1854 and 1857-1861, of Sarah North Sallie Leftwich while a student at Valley Union Seminary in Botetourt County, Virginia. Also includes transcripts of letters to her family, friends, and prospective employers for teaching positions. Also includes accounts and addresses., 1 volume, 116 p.
- Letter, 16 December 1860, from Frances Jane Leftwich Shepherd, Fluvanna County, Virginia, to Sallie N. Leftwich, Bedford County, Virginia, discussing Sallie's upcoming wedding and other family and personal news., 4 p.
- Letter, 20 March 1861, from Sallie N. Leftwich, Bedford County, to Thomas J. Shepherd, Fluvanna County, expressing concern over his recent illness., 2 p.
- Letter, 3 February 1867, from John William Leftwich, Pittsylvania County, Virginia, to Frances Jane Leftwich Shepherd, Fluvanna County, describing his Civil War service, and the difficulties of running his farm in Pittsylvania County during the war and Reconstruction., 4 p.
- Letter, 3 June 1882, from Thomas J. Shepherd, Richmond, Virginia, to Sallie N. Leftwich Shepherd asking her (his mother) if he can come home from school., 1 leaf.
- Letter, 27 March [1861], from Frances Jane Leftwich Shepherd, Fluvanna County, to Sallie N. Leftwich, Bedford County, concerning her marriage and offering advice., 3 p.
- Letter, n.d. [between 1861 and 1864], from Ann Bilbro Leftwich, Bedford County, to Sallie N. Leftwich Shepherd sending family and personal news., 2 p.
- Treatise, [ca. 1865-1868], on the cultivation and curing of bright tobacco in Pittsylvania County by J. W. Leftwich., 19 p.
- Chemistry notebook, ca. 1920, of F. N. Bowles while a student at Richmond College, Richmond, Virginia., 1 volume, 120 p.
- Photograph, 1897, of Clyde Dennis Shepherd taken by C. R. Rees, Petersburg, Virginia., 1 photograph.
- Photograph, n.d., M. M. Sneed, possibly of Charlottesville or Gordonsville, Virginia, taken by Seabrook Brothers, Charlottesville., 1 photograph.
- Photograph, n.d., of [Gen. Ray?] Wood, taken by Seabrook Brothers, Charlottesville, Virginia., 1 photograph.
- Photograph, n.d., of Bertha Caldwell taken by Gottwals, Washington D.C., 1 photograph.
- Photographs, n.d., of unidentified individuals., 5 photographs.
- Photographs, n.d., of unidentified individuals., 3 photographs.
- Book, 1879, Causeries Avec Les Enfants with inscription L. E. Leftwich Shorter College Rome Ga. Oct. 28th --79., 1 volume.
- book, 1893, Sights and Scenes of the World containing photographs from nations around the globe., 1 volume.